Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco. My name is
Catherine and we've got an upper
intermediate level
lesson for you guys today.
This one is all about a
crime scene. That's right.
So we are going to
be at a crime scene.
We are with the police officers
and we're going to take a look
at some very, very
interesting and specific vocab
to like police and
a crime and all that.
That's right. So if you are
a fan of the TV show CSI
or you like some of
these investigation police
work TV shows, this
is the lesson for you.
That's right. So why don't we go and
listen to the dialogue for the first time.
All right, Officer McGraw. Give it to
me straight. What are we looking at here?
Detective McGee.
We're glad to see you.
We could sure use your
expert teeth on this one.
It's a break-in but nothing
seems to have been stolen.
We were sent to call from
the Bear family at around
1030 this morning.
They'd gone out for a walk
before breakfast and
came home to this mess.
Broken chairs and
porridge all over the place.
Apparently Mama Bear had made
the porch a little too hot you see.
They were waiting
for it to cool down.
Okay then let's start
examining the evidence.
Have the forensics
team been in yet? Yes, sir.
They found some
fingerprints on the bowls and
are analyzing them back
at the lab as we speak.
Hopefully they will be able
to identify the burglar soon.
Aha! What's this? A
strand of golden hair.
This is a very important piece
of trace evidence, McGraw.
It tells me the suspect has long golden
hair and very few men have long golden hair.
So our criminal could
be a woman. A woman?
Was she working alone?
Did she have an accomplice?
An accomplice? No. No McGraw.
She was definitely working alone.
See here there are
footprints in the porch.
Here on the floor,
small footprints.
This tells me that our
suspect is small and could
possibly be a child. A child? Surely not,
sir. We must follow the clues, McGraw.
The evidence doesn't lie. Now let's
reconstruct the crime. The suspect came in,
sat in each chair breaking the smallest
one into little pieces. Next, the porridge,
she obviously tried to eat it because it
was so hot she dropped it on the floor.
Making this mess, interesting. These
footprints seem to lead upstairs. McGraw,
did your officers clear
the scene? Well, there was
no one down here. Maybe
we forgot to check upstairs.
Hey, what's with all the noise? I'm trying
to sleep up here. There she is. Get her!
All right, we're back.
So a lot of interesting phrases
there. They are obviously
investigating a break-in.
Okay, a break-in, yeah.
So someone broke
into this family's house.
So they have to
investigate the evidence and
some of the things
that were left behind.
So now why don't we
take a look on language
take away some of the
specific words they used.
Language take away.
All right, the first word
that we have is forensics.
The forensics team.
Forensics team. So a
forensics team is a team
at a police department
or a police station that
studies the things that
are left behind after a crime.
All right, so that team goes
and collects the evidence.
So you could look at hair or fingerprints
or footprints, things like that.
A forensic team is kind
of like a team that puts
together puzzle pieces trying
to figure out what the story was.
So as you said,
the TV shows CSI.
The whole show revolves
around follows a group
of forensic scientists who go to crime
scenes and look at blood and different
pieces of evidence that are left behind.
Very cool. So one piece of evidence that a
forensics team might
look at is a fingerprint.
That's right, a fingerprint
or in the dialogue we
found fingerprint,
the plural form.
Okay, so for example, if you
go to a police station because the
police think that you have
committed a crime, the
police will take
your fingerprints.
That means they'll put your
fingers into ink and they will
they will make you push
your fingers onto piece
of paper to see what
your your fingers look like.
That's right. So our fingerprints
have a unique pattern.
Everyone has
different fingerprints.
There are no two fingerprints
alike in the world, right?
Right. So it's kind of like
a form of identification.
Very good. That's right.
So that is your fingerprint.
So moving on, we talked
about fingerprints now
and the scientists who are
investigating the crime
scene and they are talking
about a very important
piece of trace evidence.
Okay, well, let's look first
at the second word there.
We've got the word
evidence. So evidence
is something that is
usually physical like a
piece of clothing or hair
that can be used against
someone when we're
trying to prove that they
have committed a crime.
Right. So for example,
a weapon or fingerprints,
all that is evidence.
Okay. So Marco, what's
the difference between
evidence and trace
evidence? Well, as you'd notice,
you have the specific word
there trace and to trace
means to to follow or
connect to connect, right?
So what you're doing
here is you are taking
this evidence to follow
or connect the person that
committed the crime. So
for example, fingerprints
lets you know who
committed the crime. Oh, okay.
Or maybe if you have blood,
you can find out who did this crime.
Right. But what about
like a broken window?
Well, that's just evidence.
That's just let's you know
how the crime was committed.
Maybe how they got into
the house. But not who did it?
But not who did it. Okay.
So trace evidence helps you
connect the crime to the
person who committed the crime.
And while moving
on, we found that very
important piece of trace
evidence, which was a piece of
or a strand of golden
hair. And the police
ever said, well, this tells me that the
suspect has long golden hair. So a suspect.
Okay, this word is it looks exactly
the same as the word to suspect.
But be careful
because we say these
two words in different ways.
So to suspect, that's a verb.
That's right. So I
suspect Marco did it.
So that means I
think or I imagine
right, whereas a suspect, a
noun, a suspect is a person.
So the person who we think or the person
who the police think committed a crime.
Okay. Okay. So for example,
we're talking about some
trace evidence like
long blonde hair.
That means the suspect is probably
a woman and is probably blonde.
Very good. And it's interesting that
you use the verb to suspect and a suspect.
They're all because
you're not sure yet.
So this person may have
committed the crime or may not.
That's right. So we have to wait until
the trial. We have to wait until we prove
this person is guilty before we can say
that they actually committed the crime.
Very good. Okay. And
while you have a suspect
and usually you also
have somebody who is in a
complex to the crime
or to the suspect. Okay.
So a suspect, as we said,
is a person. It's a noun.
So is an accomplice. So a
accomplice is a suspect's helper.
Right. So basically,
if you're robbing a
bank and I wait outside
in the car, right, while
you're robbing the bank,
then I am an accomplice.
That's right. And under
most laws, you could be
sentenced to jail. Right.
So the accomplice usually
doesn't commit the crime.
Right. You robbed the
bank, but I just waited outside
in the car to drive you out.
So I didn't rob the bank. Right.
But sometimes accomplices
do also have guns and
shoot people or knives.
So an accomplice is basically
just the helper of the
criminal, but they can
get in trouble too.
Right. So basically, it's a
person that helps out
and knows about the crime,
but didn't tell the
police about it. Exactly.
That's a really
important aspect. Okay.
So a lot of interesting words
there, all related to crimes.
Why don't we move on
now to a couple of different
phrases that we have prepared for you
on fluency builder. Fluency builder. Okay.
I like this, this first
phrase. It's a, it's a phrase
you might hear a lot
actually in police shows.
Give it to me straight.
Actually, also, you
can use it when you just
talking to someone and
they're like, hesitant, right?
Like, I don't know
how to tell you this,
but I'm not so sure. I
don't think you're going
to like what I have to say. So
I can just say, okay, come on.
Just give it to me straight.
Okay, I don't like your
shirt. No, I'm just kidding.
That's a nice shirt. But
what you're basically
asking for is the person
to say, be honest with me.
Be direct. Be direct.
Straight can mean both of
those things, honest or
straightforward or quick.
You don't want someone to go around and
around and say lots of different things.
So I guess, yeah, that does
make sense. Give it to me straight.
Maybe comes from
straight forward.
So to be straight forward
is to not hesitate to just say
something directly and
honestly. Exactly. Okay.
So moving on to our next phrase, McGraw is
talking about the bowls and he said, well,
they are analyzing them back at
the lab as we speak as we speak.
Okay. So this is actually a phrase that
refers to time. So in this instance, what
he's basically saying is
right now they're being
analyzed right now
or in this moment.
So it's a way of indicating
that something is happening
at this very moment.
Exactly. So I could say, did
you know that the president
is giving a speech as we speak?
Okay. So that means the president is
talking right now. Exactly. As we speak.
Okay, very good phrase. Now
moving on to our third phrase,
detective McGee was talking
about reconstructing the crime.
He said, let's
reconstruct the crime.
Okay. So I don't know
if any of you watch these
crime TV shows
like Dexter or CSI.
This is my favorite part
because they tell you exactly what
they believe happened.
So to reconstruct means
to build again or to
recreate, to create again.
So basically they start
at the beginning and they
pretend to follow what
happened during the crime.
So that's basically the
verb to reconstruct to
rebuild recreate. Okay.
Reconstruct the crime.
Very good. And what
about our last phrase? Okay.
So our last phrase is again
a very typical police phrase.
You hear this a lot when there's been a
crime or on TV when they're talking about
the scene of the crime.
That means the place where
the crime happened.
And the police say we need
to clear the scene or did
the officers clear the scene?
So to clear means
to empty out. Right.
But they're not talking
about emptying out the the
evidence or removing
everything from the house.
They're just saying to
remove people, right?
Right. Or obstructions.
Exactly. And why is it
that a police officer
would want to make all
the people go away? Well,
because you don't want
people stepping on
the evidence or maybe
putting their fingerprints
all over the place.
Right. So it's very
important that the officers,
the police officers clear
the scene so that they
can start their investigation.
Right. Very good.
A lot of interesting
phrases there.
I think we should go back. Why
don't we listen to the dialogue
for the last time and
we'll come back and talk
a little bit more this and
a little bit more about
this really interesting
topic. All right, Officer
McGraw, give it to me straight.
What are we looking at here?
Detective McGee, we're glad
to see you. We could sure use
your expertise on this one. It's a break-in,
but nothing seems to have been stolen.
We were sent to call from
the Bear family at around 10,
30 this morning. They'd
gone out for a walk
before breakfast and
came home to this mess.
Broken chairs and
porridge all over the place.
Apparently, Mama Bear had
made the porch a little too hot.
You see, they were
waiting for it to cool down.
Okay, then, let's start
examining the evidence.
Have the friends 16 been in yet?
Yes, sir. They found
some fingerprints on the
bowls and are analyzing them
back at the lab as we speak.
Hopefully, they will
be able to identify
the burglar soon. What's
this? A strand of golden hair.
This is a very
important piece of trace
evidence, McGraw. It
tells me the suspect has
long golden hair and very
few men have long golden hair.
So our criminal could
be a woman. A woman?
Was she working alone?
Did she have an accomplice?
In accomplice, no. No, McGraw.
She was definitely working alone.
See, here there are
footprints in the porridge.
Here on the floor,
small footprints.
This tells me that our
suspect is small and could
possibly be a child.
A child? Surely not, sir.
We must follow the clues,
McGraw. The evidence doesn't lie.
Now, let's
reconstruct the crime.
The suspect came in, sat in
each chair breaking the smallest
one into little pieces.
Next, the porridge, she
obviously tried to eat
it because it was so hot.
She dropped it on the
floor, making this mess.
Interesting. These footprints
seem to lead upstairs.
McGraw. Did your
officers clear the scene?
Well, there was no one down here.
Maybe we forgot to check upstairs.
Hey, what's with all the noise?
I'm trying to sleep up
here. There she is. Get her!
You mentioned a couple
of different shows, such as
Dexter and CSID. Do you
watch any of these shows?
I do. I'm a big fan
of Dexter. Dexter.
And Dexter, as you know,
works at a police station in Miami,
and his character
is in forensics.
He analyzes blood. Right.
He's like a blood expert.
Yes. But it's interesting because
he commits crimes himself.
He uses his knowledge to help
him to not get caught. Right.
So he's both a criminal,
and he's a police officer.
But he's kind of like a superhero criminal,
right? Because he doesn't kill for a fun
or a pleasure. He just takes out
people who kind of deserve it, right? Yes.
But he does kind of do it for
pleasure because he's obsessed.
He can't not kill.
So instead of killing
good people, he decides he
will only ever kill bad people.
It's a really good show.
I've watched a couple of
episodes, and it's very, very good.
The same as CSID. There
are a couple of different
versions of CSID Miami,
New York, and Las Vegas.
But my favorite is Las
Vegas. Very, very good.
And also Law and Order.
I've watched a couple
of episodes of Law and
Order. It's pretty good.
Yeah, they often talk
about forensics because
they have both parts.
They have the police part
and the law part with
the lawyers who have to
use the evidence in
court. Very interesting.
And there's also, well, forensics
scientists, they take a look at the evidence.
But I think also they examine the
body back at the morgue, right?
That's right. They
look at the body
to find out what happened to the body. This
is all a part of reconstructing the crime.
So this person is also
sometimes called a corner, right?
Okay. The person
who analyzes the body.
It's pretty scary though.
I think if you think
about having to, you
know, to analyze a body,
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
I don't even know how somebody
becomes a forensic
scientist, for example.
Do you study this as well? Yeah,
they have lots of forensic programs.
I think I saw in the Discovery Channel,
they have a reality TV show about, you know,
students, forensic
students, and they're actually
taking three of crime
scenes and then they
get eliminated one by
one. I have to look it up.
Well, I'm curious to know,
have you ever heard of this
before, forensic science
or forensic anthropology?
There are lots of people
who study this and
who do this as a job and
if you're not interested
in that, maybe you could
tell us about what kind
of crime drama TV shows you like
because we certainly love them here.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
All right. We'll see everyone there. Bye.